Without further ado, we're going to get stuck into it.
그럼 지체 없이 get it로 들어가 보죠
Talking about Laura.
로라 말이에요
Low rank adaptation.
낮은 순위 적응력이죠
And this is going to be a section where we will talk a bit of theory for a few slides, but fear not,
이 섹션에서 슬라이드 몇 개 동안 이론에 관해 얘기할 거예요 하지만 걱정 마세요 늘 그렇듯 바로
we're going to get straight to practice as usual.
연습할 거니까요 Get in get
The best way to understand these things is by seeing them in action.
이런 걸 이해하는 가장 좋은 방법은 직접 보는 거예요
So just after a couple of slides, we're going to hit Colab and look at these things for reals.
슬라이드 몇 개 본 후에 Colab을 누르고 실제로 살펴보죠
But first just to set the context then.
하지만 먼저 컨텍스트를 설정하죠
So look we're going to be using llama 3.1 for this for this week.
자, llama 3을 사용할 거예요 이번 주에 1달러예요
And llama 3.1 comes in three sizes.
라마 3도요 1은 세 가지 사이즈가 있어요
It comes in the 8 billion parameter size the 70 billion and then the monstrous 405 billion size.
80억 매개 변수로 700억에 달하는 거대한 규모입니다 무려 4050억이죠
Um, and of course we're taking the smaller one, the 8 billion.
물론 더 작은 80억 달러도 받을 거예요
Um, but even that is going to be way too large for us to be training realistically on, on the sort
하지만 그것도 너무 커질 거예요 현실적으로 훈련하기에는요 하나의 GPU
of box we want to be able to pay for, like a one GPU box, um, 8 billion weights is already that's
박스에 지불하고 싶은 비용으로요 80억 개의 무게라면 램
32GB of Ram.
32GB죠
If you add it up, It's, it's and that's just to have the model in memory when you start training it,
모두 더하면 메모리 안에 있는 모델이 됩니다. 훈련을 시작할 때 최적화
which is about running optimization, where you have to be able to get gradients for each of these weights.
실행을 할 수 있습니다. 각각의 값에 따라 그러데이션을 얻을 수 있어야 하죠.
Um, that that's something which would consume way too much memory.
메모리를 너무 많이 쓰는 거예요
We wouldn't have a hope.
희망이 없었을 거예요
Um, and so it would also take a hugely long amount of time because there would be so much to, to be
시간도 엄청나게 오래 걸릴 거예요 최적화할 게 너무 많으니까요 80억
optimizing across be optimizing these 8 billion weights.
개의 무게를 최적화하려면요
That's that's just a lot of processing.
처리할 게 많네요
Um, and it's the kind of thing, of course, that these, uh, made that these frontier labs and places
물론 이런 프런티어 연구소와 메타 연구소들이 대형 모델에
like meta have spent very large sums of money for the biggest models, more than $100 million it costs
많은 돈을 투자한 덕분이죠 한 대를 훈련하는 데 1억 달러 이상이 들었어요
And so that, you know, probably not the kind of money we're going to be spending.
그래서 아마 우리가 쓸 만한 돈은 아닐 거예요
Uh, so there are some techniques, some tricks, uh, which make it surprisingly low cost to train,
그래서 기본 모델을 훈련하는 데 놀라울 정도로 적은 비용과 요령이 필요합니다 그래야 특정
uh, from a base model so that you can make something that's better at achieving your particular task,
작업을 더 잘 수행할 수 있으니까요 기본 모델이 원래
Assuming that it's got a lot in common with what the base model was originally trained to do.
훈련받은 것과 공통점이 많다고 가정하면요
Um, so before I explain what Lora is, let me just quickly summarize the llama architecture.
로라가 뭔지 설명하기 전에 라마 건축 양식을 간단히 요약해 볼게요
Now, we're not going to get into deep into neural network architecture in this course.
Get in GAME 이 과정에선 신경망 구조를 깊이 다루진 않을 거예요
It's something which we'll I'll give you some insight, some intuition behind without going into a lot
아주 자세히는 설명하지 않고 직관적으로 설명해 드릴게요
But the llama 3.1 architecture consists of stacks and stacks of layers of, of neurons.
라마 3은 어때요? 뉴런이 층층이 쌓여 있는 형태예요
Um, it's actually got 32 groups of these layers where each group consists.
각 그룹이 구성된 이런 레이어 그룹이 32개예요
So each group is called a llama decoder layer.
각 그룹을 라마 디코더 층이라고 해요
And it has in it some self-attention layers, some multi-layer perceptron layers and a silo activation
자기 주의력 계층과 다중 인터셉트론 계층 사일로 활성화 계층과 표준 계층이
layer and layer norm.
있어요
And we'll see this in a second.
잠시 후에 이걸 보죠
You don't you maybe you know what this is already.
이미 어떤 상황인지 알고 있을지도 몰라요
If you've got a theoretical background.
이론적 배경이 있다면요
If not, it's going to be be more real, be more tangible.
그렇지 않다면 더 현실적이고 실재할 거예요
When you see this architecture in Colab in just a second.
콜랍에 있는 이 건축물을 보면요
Um, And all of these parameters sticking in this, in this big, uh, this, this, this, uh, layered
이 모든 매개 변수들이 이 큰, 이 계층 아키텍처에 달라붙어 32기가
architecture take up 32 gigs of memory.
메모리를 차지해요
So this is now the big idea behind Lora.
이게 로라의 원대한 아이디어예요
The idea is, look, what we can do is we can first freeze all of these weights.
우선 이 추들을 전부 얼릴 거예요
Normally, during optimization, you you do a forward pass through your neural network.
보통 최적화 과정에서는 신경망을 통해 전진 패스를 해요
You figure out how, um, you look at the prediction, the next token that your network predicted,
네트워크가 예측한 다음 토큰을 어떻게 분석할지 살펴보고 원래 토큰이 있어야
you compare it with what the token should have been, what is the actual true next token.
할 것과 비교해 보세요 진짜 다음 토큰이 무엇일까요?
And then based on that, you figure out how much would you want to shift each of the different weights
그런 다음 그걸 바탕으로 각 비트를 조금씩 바꿔서
a little bit in order to make it so that next time it's a little bit better at predicting the right
다음번에는 올바른 토큰을 예측할 수 있도록 하는 거죠
That's the idea of optimization.
그게 최적화의 개념이죠
A bit hand-wavy, but you get the idea.
약간 웨이브 비트 같지만 느낌은 오죠 get it get it
Literally.
말 그대로요
Hand-wavy.
수작업으로요
Uh uh, but uh, the the concept of Lora is, first of all, frees all these weights.
하지만 로라의 콘셉트는 우선 이 모든 역기를 자유롭게 한다는 거죠
We're not actually going to optimize these 8 billion weights because it's just too much, too many things,
80억 개의 무게는 최적화하지 않을 겁니다 너무 많으니까요 너무 많은 노브와
too many knobs to turn to, too many gradients.
그러데이션이 있어요
Instead, we pick a few of the layers that we think are the key things that we'd want to train.
대신 훈련하고 싶은 핵심 사항을 몇 가지 골라요
And these layers, these modules in this, this stacked, uh, layered architecture are known as the
이 층과 모듈 안에 이렇게 층층이 쌓인 구조물을 목표 모듈이라고
target modules.
해요
So that's where this expression target modules comes from.
그래서 이 표현 대상 모듈이 있는 거죠
That I said, sounds a bit like something out of Star Trek, but it just means the the layers of the
스타트렉에 나오는 비트 같다고 했는데 신경망의 층을
neural network that you will be focusing on for the purposes of training, but the weights will still
말하는 거예요 훈련에 집중할 수 있지만 무게는 여전히 얼어
be frozen.
있죠
Instead, you will create new matrices called adapter matrices with fewer dimensions, so not as many
대신 새로운 매트릭스인 어댑터 매트릭스를 소개할 거예요 적은 수의 치수죠 실제 치수에
dimensions as are in the the real guy.
비해서 치수가 많지는 않아요
These will be smaller dimensionality or lower rank.
입체감이 작거나 계급이 낮을 거예요
It's called um and and they will be off to one side, and you will have the technique for applying these
이 물질을 한쪽으로 몰면 이 물질을 표적 모듈에 바르는 기술을 익힐
matrices into the target modules.
수 있어요
So they will they will adapt the target modules.
그래서 목표 모듈을 수정할 거예요
There'll be a formula which I will tell you about in a second.
공식이 있는데 잠시 후에 말씀드릴게요
But that formula will mean that that in the future, whatever values are in those blue low rank adapters
하지만 이 공식은 미래에는 저 파란색 로 랭크 어댑터에 있는 값이 조금씩 바뀔
will slightly shift.
거라는 걸 의미하죠
We'll slightly change what goes on in the target modules.
대상 모듈에서 일어나는 일을 약간 바꿀 거예요
They adapt them so it's lower rank, it's lower dimensional, fewer weights that will be applied against
등급도 낮고 차원도 낮아서 표적 모듈에 가해지는 무게가 적게 들도록
these target modules.
개조했어요
And then there's one little technicality because you'll see this in a second.
잠시 후에 보시겠지만 기술적인 문제가 있어요
It's worth mentioning, in fact, because of the way that the dimensions work in these neural networks,
이 말을 꼭 해야겠네요 이런 신경망에서 치수가 작동하는 방식을
there are in fact two of these low rank matrices, one one is known as a and one is known as B.
보면 낮은 순위의 행렬은 두 가지예요 하나는 A, 하나는 B죠
And you'll see in the code they're called lora a and lora b.
코드에는 로라 a와 로라 b라고 적혀 있어요
So there are two matrices.
행렬은 두 가지가 있어요
It's not super important to know that, but I want to make sure that when you see it in the code.
그걸 아는 게 그리 중요하진 않지만 코드에서 그걸 보시도록 확실히 해두고 싶어요
You'll see this and you'll say, okay, there are two matrices.
이걸 보면 두 행렬이 있다고 생각할 거예요
They get applied to target modules.
Get을 대상 모듈에 적용해요
This makes sense.
말 되네요
And that at a high level is the story behind Laura Freas.
로라 프레스의 숨은 이야기가 아주 깊어요
The main model come up with a bunch of of smaller matrices with fewer dimensions.
본래는 치수가 적은 작은 행렬을 많이 만들었어요
These are subject to training.
훈련 대상이죠
They will get trained and then they will be applied using some simple formula to the target modules.
get을 훈련한 다음 간단한 공식을 이용해 목표 모듈에 적용할 거예요
And that way you'll be able to make a base model that will get better and better as it learns.
그렇게 기본 모델을 만들 수 있어요 get이 학습할수록 더 좋아지는 거죠
Because of the application of these Laura matrices.
로라 매트릭스 응용 프로그램 덕분이죠
And Laura stands for low rank adaptation because they are lower rank, lower dimensions and they adapt
로라는 낮은 서열의 적응을 의미해요 서열도 낮고, 공간도 낮고 목표 모듈에
the target modules.
적응하거든요
There we go.
됐어요
A lot of talking, a lot of words, but hopefully you've got an intuition for how this fits together,
많은 대화와 단어가 오가지만 잘 조합할 수 있는 직관을 가지길
and that intuition will become clearer when you see it in the code.
바랍니다 코드를 보면 그 직관이 더 명확해질 거예요
Um, but in the next session, we'll just talk quickly about one more thing, which is the Q, the quantization.
다음 시간엔 하나만 더 간단히 얘기할게요 Q, 퀀타이즈요